Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 1-9 FA789A
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 1-9
1914-1981, bulk 1946-1981
1946-1961
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
Lee, Ivy L. (Ivy Ledbetter) (1877-1934)
Jamieson, Francis A.
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman (1910-2004)
Rockefeller, David (1915-2017)
Rockefeller, Winthrop (1912-1973)
Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison) (1906-1978)
FA789A
37.6 Cubic Feet 73 document boxes, 2 half document boxes, 5 flat boxes
Biographical / Historical
After World War II the Rockefeller family office grew rapidly as John D. Rockefeller Jr.'s sons began actively working in the office. One new department established in 1946 was that of Public Relations. Under the direction of Francis A. Jamieson the Public Relations department initially spent most of its efforts on Nelson A. Rockefeller's Latin American activities. The department also prepared press releases and offered public relations advise to the other brothers and occasionally for JDR Jr. In many ways the department also became the eyes and ears of the office. Two newspaper clipping services were engaged as well as a radio monitoring service. The clippings and reports were circulated among the five brothers and clipping scrapbooks -- which appear in FA789, Series 12 -- were made. As the activities of the brothers grew during the 1950s and 1960s the Public Relations department was given increasing responsibilities in the preparation of family and office policy toward a great variety of social, economic and cultural activities. To provide sufficient background on this expanding universe the department established research files which were maintained by staff. The department also collected periodical literature containing articles about or of interest to the Rockefellers. This literature was not systematically collected or compiled. The PR department also inherited a backlog of magazine articles from the files of various administrative assistants. One important source of back periodicals that are now included in this collection are the files kept by Robert W. Gumbel, once private secretary to JDR Jr. and later office manager.
Arrangement
This collection was arranged by Joseph W. Ernst, the Rockefeller family archivist and first director of the Rockefeller Archive Center.
1. American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA)
2. International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC)
3. Administration and Staff
4. General – United States
5. General – Foreign
6. Politics
7. Family Members and Interests
8. Articles and Books Correspondence
9. Ivy Lee Correspondence and Clippings
Scope and Contents
The Public Relations Department papers document the general activities and public opinion of the Rockefeller family during the years 1946-1961. Nelson, Winthrop, Laurance, David, and JDR 3rd are mentioned most frequently throughout the collection. The collection is primarily made up of correspondence between Rockefeller brothers and various public relations employees, studies, administrative files, articles and clippings. A large amount of material relates to Nelson's foreign aid projects in Venezuela and Brazil, specifically the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) (Series 1) and the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) (Series 2). Nelson's political campaigns are documented heavily as well (see Series 6, Politics, 1941-1960).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Separated Materials
Special format items have been separated from the body of the collection and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
Public relations; Public relations and politics; Rockefeller family -- Public opinion
- American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA), 1946-1960; 1; 4.18 Cubic Feet 11 letter document boxes
  - General, 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    Scope and Contents
    Statements of organization, activities and objectives; chronological history. Descriptions of listings of AIA in Encyclopedia of American Associations; Encyclopedia Britannica; Directory of Pan American Societies in the USA.
  - Certificates of Incorporation - By-Laws, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological History, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Community Services Program - Sao Paulo, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Contributions, 1948-1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Contributions made by AIA to Catholic University, Caracas; Uhiao Cultural Brasil - Estados Unidos. Way in which requests made to AIA should be handled. FAJ, Bernardo Jofre, Pete Hudges, MD, Henry Bagley, John Camp.
  - Finances, 1951-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Budgets; Fund raising programs, fee for public relations counseling services rendered to Rockefeller Brothers Fund. RBF grants to AIA. Financial statements. FAJ, J.W. Hisle, Ed Stuntz, Walter Crawford, W. K. Harrison, Dana Creel, MD.
  - Historical Sketch - E. A. Stuntz, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Not issued as AIA history - suggested that it be published as a book and sequel to Stuntz's previous story on IIAA "To Make People Strong". Ed. Stuntz, FAJ, MD
  - IBEC, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Two separate corporations - differences. AIA-IBEC Coordination Committee. John R. Camp, J. W. Hisle.
  - IDS Release, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    AIA agreement with International Development Services, Inc. to have IDS furnish some managerial services (CBR program). IDS breakaway group from AIA's NY office headed by Robert (Pete Hudgens). IDS proposes to make services available under contract to groups and organizations in US for operations abroad. Pete Hudges, FM, NAR
  - Informe, 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Description of AIA activities in Venezuela and Brazil. Flor Brennan.
  - Jones and French Report - Appraisal of Major Programs, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    Appraisal of major AIA programs in Venezuela and Brazil based on a study (Fall 1960 - Spring 1961) by John French and Arthur Jones.
  - National Planning Association, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Non-political, non-profit and fact finding organization publishes pamphlets on various subjects (regional studies, reports on key domestic and international issues) in attempt to wield informal influence on government policy. WR and NAR declinations to serve on various committees. Gold medal for outstanding contribution through Planning to Betterment of Human Life to NAR - 1955. RBF conditional pledge of 10,000 dollars to NPA in 1952. FAJ, Pete Hudgens, NAR, WR, H. C. Sonne.
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1948-1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Members of board, FAJ, JDR Jr. resignation. FAJ, Walter L. Crawford, Mary C. Rockefeller, MD
  - Programs and Future Programs, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Expansion and proposed new activities and functions.
  - Progress Report, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Printed booklet with photos - 1946 -1960; 1960-1965 programs; financial reports.
  - Publications, 1949-1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Agricultural Publications project. Magazine articles.
  - Record, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Printed publication - coming out 3 times yearly. Consists of stories re: the work of AIA and its subsidiaries and affiliated organizations - written by AIA staff and distributed to employees of all organizations involved with AIA and other interested people. Copies of AIA Record Number 2 and Number 3.
  - Annual Reports, 1950-1957 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Caracas - Venezuela - 3rd Quarterly Report, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Caracas - Venezuela - 4th Quarterly Report, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mr. John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1955; 1960 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Declines to give in 1955. 500,000 dollar gift to AIA in 1960. Wallace K. Harrison, JDR Jr., FAJ, Philip F. Keebler
  - United Fruit Company, 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    United Fruit - supposed similarity of public relations programs with AIA's point IV. UFC and AIA decision not to work together.
  - Newsletters, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 26-29)
    Stories on various phases of AIA work - series of stories. Distributed on the average of twice a week.
  - Oil Companies, 1947-1956 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Financial support for AIA programs by oil companies i.e. Creole Petroleum, Compagnia Shell de Venezuela; Mem Grande; International Petro; Socony Mobil Oil of Venezuela. Disagreements over amount of oil companies' publicity as participants in AIA. Question whether to put representative from oil company on AIA board. Bernardo Jofre, FAJ, NAR, John Camp.
  - Overseas Policy Manual, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Press Releases, 1946-1958 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Training Manual - Jamieson, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Brazil, 1947-1960 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Status of programs throughout Brazil i.e. Minas Gerais, Sao Paulo, Santa Rita, Sao Jose - proposed Point IV project in Sao Francisco Valley. Expansion of programs. Finances - Budgets, question of continuation of support from Corn Products Com. to AIA Brazil. FAJ, MD, LH Levy, Wl Crawford, JW Hisle,WKH, Henry Bagley.
  - Brazil - ABCAR - Associacao Brasileira de Credita e Assistencia Rural, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Formation of ABCAR - a private, non-profit civil society to coordinate in Brazil state and regional rural rehabilitation programs. Joao Napolcao do Andrade, Pres. of ABCAR. Problems of newly formed organization. AIA question of whether to renew its support to ABCAR after 1961 - NAR loan to Andrade 1960.
  - Brazil - ABCAR - Informer, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Brazil - ACAR - Annual Reports, 1951-1959 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Brazil - ACAR - Bulletin, 1952-1960 (Box 5, Folder 39-40)
    ACAR Boletim Informativo.
  - Brazil - ACAR - Information Program, 1949-1959 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Brazil - ANCAR - Associacao Nordestina de Credito e Assistencia Rural, 1954-1958 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    Formation of ANCAR, 1954 AIA with Banco do Brasil and Banco do Nordeste do Brasil. Broader version of ACAR to help farmers in Brazil's northeast drought area. Walter Crawford, Henry Bagley.
  - Brazil - Articles by J.B. Griffing, 1950-1955 (Box 5, Folder 43-44)
  - Brazil - Home Demonstration and Service Project with SAPS, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Brazil - Livestock Parasite Control and Demonstration, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Central America, 1950-1960 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    Various proposals for programs in Central America. Financing. James G. Maddox
  - Columbia, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Possible AL program in Columbia requested by Minister of Agriculture Arango Lodono. AIA unwilling to supply funds.
  - Honduras, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    Sr. Joaquim Bogran Fiallos head of Honduras School Nutrition program requesting AIA assistance for a National Social Service Program.
  - India, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    AIA and Cooperative League of the US working through the Indian Cooperative Union (India) to study economic and social problems. Thomas Keehn (rep. AIA and CL) consultant in India to ICU. Keehn 's involvement with ICU Project and All India Cooperative Union (AICU).
  - Iran, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    Camp proposal for possible AIA operation in Iran with Iranian Oil Company support. Walter L. Crawford, John R. Camp.
  - Keehn, Thomas B., 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 52-54)
    Letters re his activities as consultant to ICU and also personal news. Murray D. Lincoln, Tom Keehn, NAR, LHL, Walter L. Crawford, MD.
  - Peru, 1950-1955 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    Discussions, proposals for possible AIA program in Peru; Interest by Peruvian government. Problems in financing, etc. Delay.
  - Venezuela, 1947-1956 (Box 6, Folder 56-57)
    Status of various programs in Venezuela - purpose, function and objectives of AIA in Venezuela. John Camp, Bernardo Jofre, LH Levy, FAJ
  - Venezuela - Base Program, 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    Base program's function seen as laying a foundation for more defined AIA work in Venezuela. Pete Hudgens.
  - Venezuela - Community Service, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 59)
  - Venezuela - Cooperation in Venezuela, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - Venezuelan Government Agreements, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    Basic contract, CIDEA and CBR contracts, press release - extension of AIA program in Venezuela for 3 years
  - Venezuela - Analysis of Brazilian and Venezuelan Comment on AIA Proposals, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    Editorial comment seen as favorable from Brazil but unfavorable on several points from Venezuela; excerpts from newspaper articles.
  - Venezuela - Future Programs, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    Proposals and recommendations for changes and additions to programs.
  - Venezuela - Tachira Road Project, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    Widening and improving road
  - Venezuela - Turrialba - Costa Rica, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    Asociacion de Promociones Agricolas de Turrialba, Association of Agricultural Graduates of Turrialba - to aid in coordination of rural economy problems
  - Venezuela - Training Project, 1947-1956 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    The training of Venezuelans in all phases of AIA programs - i.e. technical training (sanitation, grain disease); teacher training, etc.
  - CBR - Loveridge Report, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    An Administrative Study of the Department of Forestry of the Ministry of Agriculture by Earl Overdige through CBR. John Heilman.
  - CBR - Consejo de Bienestar Rural, 1948-1960 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    Council for Rural Work. CBR expansion of functions from very general - program of improving the physical environments of the people (health, housing) and training and education of rural population with emphasis on agricultural instruction to more specialized functions within framework of Venezuela government programs
  - CBR - Andean Study - Heilman Law, 1953-1956 (Box 8, Folder 69)
  - CBR - MAC Charles H. Bernhard Report, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    Suggestions for creating more effective Public Relations and information program for MAC. Howard E. Law, Howard Knowles, FAJ
  - CBR - MAC Information Program, 1955-1957 (Box 8, Folder 71-72)
    Includes agricultural information disseminated through publications, pictures, radio. Mobile exhibit - NY. Much of the work done by Schuyler Brandt.
  - CBR - Progress Report, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 73)
  - CBR - Annual Reports, 1948-1952 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - CBR - Monthly Reports, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 75-76)
  - CEV - Consejo de Educacion Vocational, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - CEV - Venezuela, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 78-80)
    Vocational Education Council. Function would be reorganization of rural primary and vocational trade and industrial education. Similarity of OAS plan. Objections of Venezuelan government. Question of whether program would justify itself. Delay in formation of CEV. John Camp, Walter Crawford, E. E. Maes.
  - CIDEA - General, 1948-1954 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    Primary function - dissemination of nutrition information among all elements of Venezuelan pop. Status of various projects. Decision not to have CIDEA disseminate UN information. Standard Brands interest in CIDEA program. Possibility of expanding CIDEA program to other Latin and South American countries. E. Stuntz, Nelson Riley.
  - CIDEA - Government Contracts - Agreement, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    Problems - disagreements with Venezuelan government. Camp signing informal agreement - strong disapproval by AIA board - modification of agreement and signing July 1, 1954. MSAS (Ministry of Health and Social Assistance) and INN (National Nutrition Institute).
  - CIDEA - Government Contracts - Transfer to Venezuelan Government, 1956-1957 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    CIDEA - 8 years old transferred to Venezuelan Government in 1956
  - CIDEA - Projects - San Casimiro, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    Trying to apply principals used in Caracas CIDEA program in San Casimiro, in a backward agricultural community.
  - CIDEA - Projects - Cantaura, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    Second CIDEA project, in a district rich in oil.
  - CIDEA - Planning Future Programs, 1949-1954 (Box 10, Folder 86)
  - CIDEA - Finances, 1950-1951 (Box 10, Folder 87)
  - CIDEA - Honduras, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    Honduras Nutrition Program. SAEH Servicio de Alimentacion Escolar Hondure. Working with IIAA and others. Asks CIDEA and IIAA assistance. Budget - Organization.
  - CIDEA - Peru, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    Peruvian government interest in CIDEA assistance with Peruvian National Nutrition program. Information on Peru.
  - CIDEA - Dr.Gonzalez Puccini, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    Dr. Gonzalez Puccini - Director del Institute Nacional de Nutricion, Venezuela. Cordial letters exchanged praising work of CIDEA and Dr. Puccini, but discord over policy. Relieved of his duties as head of CIDEA in 1952 for "alleged close friendship with a leader of one of 3 Venezuelan political parties."
  - CIDEA - Nutrition and Information, 1947-1955 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    Printed descriptive material on Nutrition Information Program in Venezuela. Purpose: Simple training and technical direction to families in rural areas in agriculture, food preparation, nutrition and home management
  - CIDEA - Nutrition Days, 1951-1954 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    Roles of media in aiding Nutrition information program. Venezuela celebrated National Nutrition Day - first celebration in 1951. Martin Reynolds.
  - CIDEA - Films - S. Bradt, 1949-1954 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    Commissioned to write films and produce them. Budgets.
  - CIDEA - Films - S. Bradt - "Food for a Strong People", 1949 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    Master Script
  - CIDEA - Radio Programs, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    Scripts
  - CIDEA - Publications, 1949-1956 (Box 11, Folder 96-99)
    Posters (7 Basic foods), comic type book program, pamphlets. Suggestion for school book program, considered dangerous venture in foreign country - trying to interfere with educational policies and ideas is the reason why project not considered. Napkins promotional. Budgets. Many different pamphlets.
  - Press Releases - Robert Hudgens, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 100)
  - Press Releases - Berent Friele, 1946 (Box 11, Folder 101)
- International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), 1947-1961; 2; 7.98 Cubic Feet 21 letter document boxes
  - General, 1947-1961; 1
    - Certificate of Incorporation - By-Laws, 1947-1950 (Box 11, Folder 102)
    - General, 1947-1961 (Box 12, Folder 103-104)
      Formation of IBEC, newspaper comment; company policies. Plans for internal organization, company description: statement of functions, objectives, etc. Reorganization. Report on IBEC by Univ. of Minnesota scholar. Expansion. NAR, FAJ.
    - AIA Story, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 105)
      Paper on various functions, objectives, etc. of each organization. Basic differences.
    - The IBEC Story, 1955-1956 (Box 12, Folder 106)
      Proposed publication, project delayed indefinitely. MD, HK, FAJ.
    - Corporate Structure, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - Publicity, 1947-1957 (Box 12, Folder 108)
      Articles on various phases of IBEC's activities, magazine and newspaper. Attacks from press. NAR, FAJ
    - Annual Reports, 1947-1959 (Box 13, Folder 109-111)
    - Record-CronicadeIBEC, 1949-1953 (Box 13, Folder 112)
      Printed booklets. Record: 1949, 1951, 1952. Cronica de IBEC: (Spanish ed. of Record) 1951, 1953.
    - Personnel - Labor, 1947-1961 (Box 13, Folder 113)
      Appointments, resignations; withdrawal of Nelson Riley from IBEC in Brazil upon request of Brazilian T. Quartim Barbosa. NAR 's returning in 1956 from Eisenhower administration to presidency of IBEC. General industrial and labor relations - problems, policies. Employee benefits; pension plan, incentive bonus plan. K. J. Kadow, LHL, Nelson Riley, NAR, FAJ
    - Published Articles, 1947-1958 (Box 13, Folder 114-115)
    - Supermarkets - General, 1956-1959 (Box 14, Folder 116)
      Information and comparisons of the various supermarkets in SA. Supermarket expansion program, 1956-1959.
    - Supermarkets - Brazil, 1951-1956 (Box 14, Folder 117)
      Question of whether to start a supermarket operation in Brazil - memos, surveys, estimates. Decision to go ahead - R. W. Boogaart accepting managership of supermarket enterprises. FAJ, MD, Berent Friele, A. Vandenburg, R. W. Boogaart.
    - Supermarkets - Europe, 1956-1957 (Box 14, Folder 118)
      Supermarket possibilities in Western Europe. Recommends Italy and Belgium as countries ready for immediate development. R. W. Boogaart.
    - Supermarkets - Italy, 1957-1961 (Box 14, Folder 119)
      Formation of a supermarket company in Milan, Italy. By 1960 5 supermarkets in Milan, more stores opened in Florence. Success of markets. Steven David, Rolland Hood, Richard Boogaart.
    - Supermarkets - Peru, 1955-1956 (Box 14, Folder 120)
      Opening supermarkets in Lima - "Todos", also TODOS shopping center, market plus 20 shops.
    - Supermarkets - Puerto Rico, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 121)
      Supermerado TODOS opened in 1957 in San Juan. Purpose of supermarkets: lower cost for quality foods, incentive for increased agricultural production and food processing on the Island. Prices same as main competitor, problem. TODOS opened restaurant and soda fountain, sponsored annual beef cattle competition, etc. Problem of minimum wage paid to workers. Sale of TODOS to Grand Union.
    - Supermarkets - Venezuela, 1949-1961 (Box 14, Folder 122)
      First IBEC venture into supermarket area. Venezuelan co. TODOS opened retail store (avoidance of calling it a supermarket) in Maracaibo in December 1949. Expansion to other sites. Is the IBEC chain of markets getting too large. Consolidation of markets. FAJ, Bernardo Jofre.
    - Industria Lactea de Carabobo (INLACA), 1949-1958 (Box 14, Folder 123)
      Distribution of milk. Price policy - high prices of milk causing strong criticism and complaint. Distribution of "7 Lochas" milk successful, lower priced. Studying possibility of expanding milk industry to Pueto Rico. FAJ, Bernardo Jofre, Ann Michelson, MD.
    - Industria Lactea de Carabobo (INLACA) - Annual Reports, 1952; 1956 (Box 14, Folder 124)
    - Investment Proposals and Policies, 1950-1961 (Box 14, Folder 125)
      Brazilian Forge project; Belgian Congo mining exploration; oil investments Greece. Policy on extractive industries.
    - Geneva, Switzerland, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 126)
      IBEC establishing subsidiary in Geneva as a vehicle for expanding IBEC interests in Western Europe. Steven David, Felix Kalinski.
    - CCCI - Compagnie du Congo Pour le Commerce et l'Industria - J. Jennen - Belgian Congo, Africa, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 127)
      An affiliate of Societe Generale. Rockefeller group plans to collaborate with CCCI in studying, financing and developing new industrial and agricultural projects in Africa. Emmet Hughes.
    - Industrial Credit and Investment Corp. of India - RBI Inc., 1954 (Box 14, Folder 128)
      Induxtrial Credit aid in channeling capital for expansion of industrial potential of India from private investors in England, India and USA (RBI Inc. one of the investors.)
    - MIDEC - Middle East Industrial Development Projects Corp., 1960 (Box 14, Folder 129)
      MIDEC designed to assist countries of Middle East toward industrialization. Acts as intermediary between businessmen of West and East. Service Co. offered by IBEC. L. H. Levy, Steven David, Emmet Hughes.